Joan Rollenhagen Collection of Textile Industry Photographs 6722 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Joan Rollenhagen Collection of Textile Industry Photographs
1925-1950
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Joan Rollenhagen
6722 P
0.33 cubic feet
0.3 linear ft.
Gelatin silver print, photographs.
Mostly photographs of mill workers and mill interiors.
10063425
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 17, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 30, 2017
Biographical / Historical
Joseph A. Dancewicz was born in Monastzysko, Poland on March 10, 1906 and came to the U. S. in 1921. As a young man he worked as a loom fixer in Slater Mills, superintendent of the Blackstone Mill, Lonsdale Company, Blackstone, Massachusetts; manager of the Soule Mill, New Bedford; president of Sagamore Manufacturing Co., Fall River. By 1959 he was the President and Treasurer of the Hunt-Spiller Manufacturing Company in New Bedford, Massachusetts.
Joseph Dancewicz married Christine Brown in 1946.
Mr. Dancewicz died n May 23, 1978 in New Bedford.
Scope and Contents
Includes photographs of mill workers and executives at Slater Mills in Webster, Massachusetts and mill interiors of the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Massachusetts, and unknown mill interiors. Also includes a photograph of Joseph Dancewicz and a portrait of a woman with three children.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6584 G: Ralph Huey Collection of Crompton & Knowles Graphics 6584 P: Ralph Huey Collection of Crompton & Knowles Photographs 6585/001: Crompton & Knowles General Records 6585 G: Crompton & Knowles Graphics 6585 P: Crompton & Knowles Photographs 6732: Joseph Dancewicz Papers
Clerks; Combing machines; Cotton manufacture; Diesel motor; Executives; Glass fiber industry; Immigrants; Industries; Women employees; Male employees; Industrial relations; Looms; Metal castings; Polish Americans; Spinning machinery; Superintendents; Textile factories; Textile industry; Textile industry -- Management; Textile machinery; Textile workers; Weaving; Yarn -- Examinations, questions, etc; Blackstone (Mass.); Webster (Mass.); Woonsocket (R.I.); Worcester (Mass.); Dancewicz, Joseph Anthony, 1906-1978; Derrickson, H. P.; Johnson, Carl (Mill superintendent); Blackstone Mill; Crompton & Knowles Loom Works; Hunt-Spiller Manufacturing Corp. (Boston, Mass.); Lonsdale Company; Rhode Island Plush Mills (Woonsocket, R.I.); Sagamore Manufacturing Company; Slater Mills (Webster, Mass.); Soule Mill (New Bedford, Mass.)
10063425
- Photographs of mill workers and mill interiors (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Cotton weave room with workers., black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Gelatin silver print, [194-?]. Image depicts cotton weave room of unknown mill, with one male and one female worker visible. Probably Draper looms. May be the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co. in Blackstone, Mass. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
    Format: black and white photograph.
  - Item 2: Cotton weave room., black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print, [194-?]. Image depicts large cotton weave room of unknown mill, with a few workers visible. Probably Draper looms. May be the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co. in Blackstone, Mass. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
  - Item 3: Blackstone Mill executives, 1936-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts four men in suits in office of unknown mill, possibly the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. Man seated on left is Carl Johnson, superintendent (1936-40) and general superintendent (1940-46) of the Blackstone Mill. The man seated on the right is Joseph Dancewicz (1906-78), who worked at the Blackstone Mill from 1936 to 1952. 9 x 12.5 cm.
  - Item 4: A guest at Crompton & Knowles Loom Works, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print, [1939?]. Image depicts three men at Crompton & Knowles: man on left is H.P. Derrickson, an executive at the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass.; man in middle is Carl Johnson, superintendent (1936-40) and general superintendent (1940-46) of Blackstone; man on right is Joseph A. Dancewicz (1906-78), who was overseer of weaving and slashing for the Blackstone Mill from 1936 to 1942. 13.5 x 9 cm. (w/out mount); 14.5 x 11 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 5: A guest at Crompton & Knowles Loom Works., 1939; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts five men at Crompton & Knowles Loom Works [Worcester, Mass.]: man second from left is Carl Johnson, superintendent (1936-40) and general superintendent (1940-46) of the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass.; man second from right is H.P. Derrickson, an executive at the Blackstone Mill; man at far right is Joseph A. Dancewicz (1906-78), who was the overseer of weaving and slashing for the Blackstone Mill from 1936 to 1942. 14 x 8.5 cm. (w/out mount); 15 x 11 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 6: Joseph A. Dancewicz and H.P. Derrickson., 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts two men; man on left is Joseph A. Dancewicz (1906-78) who was overseer of weaving and slashing at the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co. in Blackstone, Mass., from 1936 until 1942; the man on the right is H.P. Derrckson who was an executive at the Blackstone Mill. 9.5 x 7.5 cm.
  - Item 7: Joseph A. Dancewicz., 1925-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image of Joseph A. Dancewicz (1906-78), who worked at the Slater Mills in Webster, Mass. from 1922 until 1936, then in the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co. in Blackstone, Mass. from 1936 until 1952. Photograph taken outside; picket fence in background. 8 x 14 cm.
  - Item 8: The Dancewicz family, 1915-1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Studio portrait of a woman with two children, most probably members of the Dancewicz family. Joseph A. Dancewicz (1906-78) is most likely the boy on the right; the other two may be his mother and sister. Note the wristwatch on the girl's right arm. This print appears to be a copy made from an earlier photograph that had tears and cracks through it. 12.5 x 17.5 cm.
  - Item 9: Group of male mill workers, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image shows posed group of male mill workers with supervisors or overseers in the Slater Mills in Webster, Mass. The group supposedly includes Joseph Dancewicz, but he does not appear to be here. See 1990.20.23 for another image taken in this room. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
  - Item 10: Group of male mill workers, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image shows posed group of male mill workers with supervisors or overseers, in the Slater Mills in Webster, Mass. The man in the center of the first row, in a suitcoat, is Joseph Dancewicz (1906-78), who worked for the Slater Mills from 1922 to 1936. 21.5 x 16.5 cm. Copy A.
  - Item 11: Group of male mill workers, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image shows posed group of male mill workers with supervisors or overseers, in the Slater Mills in Webster, Mass. The man in the center of the first row, in a suitcoat, is Joseph Dancewicz (1906-78), who worked for the Slater Mills from 1922 to 1936. Copy B, probably a copy print. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
  - Item 12: Group of male and female mill workers, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image shows posed group of male and female mill workers in the Slater Mills in Webster, Mass. The man fourth from the left in the first row, in a suit, is Joseph Dancewicz (1906-78), who worked for the Slater Mills from 1922 to 1936. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
  - Item 13: Male and female employees, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image shows posed group of male and female employees in the Slater Mills in Webster, Mass. The man in the center of the first row, in a suit, is Joseph Dancewicz (1906-78), who worked for the Slater Mills from 1922 to 1936. The woman seated on his right, in the plaid dress, is Helen Kiwack [sp?]. Copy A. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
  - Item 14: Male and female employees, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image shows posed group of male and female employees in the Slater Mills in Webster, Mass. The man in the center of the first row, in a suit, is Joseph Dancewicz (1906-78), who worked for the Slater Mills from 1922 to 1936. The woman seated on his right, in the plaid dress, is Helen Kiwack [sp?]. Copy B. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
  - Item 15: Male and female employees, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image shows posed group of male and female employees in the Slater Mills in Webster, Mass. The man in the center of the first row, in a suit, is Joseph Dancewicz (1906-78), who worked for the Slater Mills from 1922 to 1936. A different set of employees from other photos in this collection. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
  - Item 16: Male and female employees, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 17: Male and female employees, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 18: Weave room employees, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image shows posed group of male employees in the Slater Mills in Webster, Mass., grouped around a loom. The man in the suit on the left is Joseph Dancewicz (1906-78), who worked for the Slater Mills from 1922 to 1936. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
  - Item 19: Mill workers, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1947; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photo by Joseph W. Whittaker, Commercial Photographer, 128 Main St., Woonsocket, R.I. Gelatin silver print, 1947. Image depicts employees of the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co. in Blackstone, Mass., at some sort of celebration. Workers appear to be lined up to speak to Joseph Dancewicz (1906-78), second from left in the photo. Dancewicz worked for the Blackstone Mill from 1936 to 1952, as superintendent from 1944 to 1952. Calendar on the wall reads August 1947. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 20: Group of textile executives and overseers., 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts 14 men who are in management or supervisory positions of one or more textile mills. Man fifth from the left is H.P. Derrickson, an executive at the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. Man fourth from the right is Joseph Dancewicz (1906-78), who was employed by the Blackstone Mill as the overseer of weaving and slashing from 1936 to 1942. Photo taken outside unknown mill building, possibly Blackstone Mill. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
  - Item 21: Joseph Dancewicz in office, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1936-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts Dancewicz in mill office with two women office workers, identified as Margaret E. Minott and Mary J. Grady on the reverse of Copy A; mill floor visible through windows in background. Dancewicz (1906-78) was employed by the Blackstone Mill as the overseer of weaving and slashing from 1936 to 1942. Copy B. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
  - Item 22: Joseph Dancewicz in office, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1936-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts Dancewicz in mill office with two women office workers, identified as Margaret E. Minott and Mary J. Grady on the reverse of the photograph; mill floor visible through windows in background. Dancewicz (1906-78) was employed by the Blackstone Mill as the overseer of weaving and slashing from 1936 to 1942. 21.5 x 16.5 cm. Copy A
  - Item 23: Joseph Dancewicz in front of spinning frame., black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print, [194-?]. Image depicts Dancewicz on the left with an unidentified man in suit and tie on the right. Both are standing in front of a cotton spinning frame, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. Dancewicz (1906-78) was employed by the Blackstone Mill as the overseer of weaving and slashing (1936-42), as assistant superintendent (1942-44) and as superintendent (1944-52). 20.5 x 25.5 cm.
  - Item 24: Unidentified mill exterior, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print, [19--]. Image depicts exterior of mill complex, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. Mill complex in background; trees in foreground; railroad tracks run through center. 16 x 12.5 cm.
  - Item 25: Group of male and female mill workers, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts posed group of male and female mill workers of the Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., with supervisors or overseers, possibly Aldea Dancause. See 1990.20.10 for another image taken in this room. 21.5 x 16.5 cm.
  - Item 26: Rhode Island Plush Mills, Woonsocket, R.I., 1925-1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Snapshot-size image depicts exterior of mill building, partially hidden behind wooden frame building. Car parked at side of frame building; one person in front of car, two people barely visible behind brick smokestack. 7 x 11.5 cm.
  - Item 27: Group of Blackstone Mill executives., 1940-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Snapshot image depicts nine men and one woman, posed outside in a parking lot, possibly on a recreational outing. The first man standing on the left is Carl Johnson, superintendent (1936-40) and general superintendent (1940-46) of the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. The third man from the right (standing) is Joseph Dancewicz, overseer of weaving and slashing (1936-42), assistant superintendent (1942-44) and superintendent (1944-52) of the Blackstone Mill. 15.5 x 10 cm.
  - Item 28: Female mill worker at spinning machine, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts female mill worker in front of spinning machine, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. 20.5 x 25.5 cm.
  - Item 29: Cotton ribbon lappers, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts interior of mill, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass., with pre-combing cotton ribbon lappers. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 30: Whitin Model J combers, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts interior of mill, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass., with Whitin Model J combers. The bi-coil combed slivers produced slivers coiled as if one strand. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 31: Cotton roving on long draft slubbers, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts interior of mill, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass., with long draft slubbers engaged in cotton roving. Note the cart full of bobbins. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 32: Mill worker at cotton ribbon lappers, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts interior of mill, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass., with male employee working at one of the cotton ribbon lappers. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 33: Cotton spinning room, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts interior of mill, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. Large room contains Whitin machinery that does long draft spinning and ring spinning. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 34: Weave room, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts interior of mill, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. Large room contains extensive number of looms. Note the difference in alley width: the front alley is narrower, the back ("beam") alley is wider. 25.5 x 20.5 cm. Copy A
  - Item 35: Weave room, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts interior of mill, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. Large room contains extensive number of looms. Note the difference in alley width: the front alley is narrower, the back ("beam") alley is wider. Copy B. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 36: Female mill worker at combing machine (?), Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts female mill worker at machinery involved in some sort of combing process, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. 20.5 x 25.5 cm.
  - Item 37: Motors running cotton spinning machinery, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts interior of mill, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. This view shows the motors running the cotton spinning machinery. 20.5 x 25.5 cm.
  - Item 38: Closeup of roving machinery, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts closeup view of the roving process, probably in the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. 20.5 x 25.5 cm.
  - Item 39: Closeup of drawing and twisting machinery, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts closeup view of drawing and twisting machinery, probably in the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. 20.5 x 25.5 cm.
  - Item 40: Spinning room with male employees, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts interior of mill, probably the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. Two male employees tend the spinning machinery. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 41: Yarn inspection, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts closeup view of yarn inspection as it comes off a machine, probably in the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. Copy A. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 42: Yarn inspection, Blackstone Mill, Blackstone, Mass., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts closeup view of yarn inspection as it comes off a machine, probably in the Blackstone Mill of the Lonsdale Co., Blackstone, Mass. Copy B. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 43: Male and female employees, Slater Mills, Webster, Mass., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)